Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions; Collection apap214
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collectionca. 1985-2012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Bowers, William J.
apap214
6 cubic ft. 170
An artificial collection of over 150 clemency petitions filed by inmates from across the United States for the lessening of their death sentence.
Historical Note
The clemency process varies from state to state and typically involves the governor, a board of advisors, or both. Clemency refers to the lessening of the penalty of the crime without forgiving the crime itself. The act of clemency is a reprieve. Unlike judicial proceedings, claims raised in clemency petitions are free of procedural defaults that can mask error, unfairness, or irrationality in a given death sentence. Petitions thus can reveal what the sentencing authority may not have known because of attorney error, prosecutorial misconduct, newly discovered evidence, or other reasons.
Scope and Contents
The Clemency Petitions Collection includes approximately 150 clemency petitions filed by inmates from across the United States. William J. Bowers originally established this collection as part of his work with The Constitution Project. Later additions were made by the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. The petition for Joseph Spaziano is from the papers of Michael A. Mello.
The collection was reformatted to PDF files in April-June 2006 and first made availible online. The petition for Joseph Spaziano was reformatted in September 2006 and the petition for Mitchell Terry Mincey was reformatted in 2012.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, and is ordered alphabetically by the petitioners last name.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by William Bowers in January 2006. The petition for Joseph Spaziano is from the papers of Michael A. Mello. The Larry Bill Elliott clemency petition was donated in 2010. Skip Hulett, Georgiana Librarian, Hargrett Rare Book and Manuscript Library, University of Georgia, provided a copy of the Mitchell Terry Mincey petition in 2012. 2006-1012
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Death Penalty; Digital Files
- Adams, James, FL, 1984 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Amrine, Joseph, MO, Death sentence overturned, released from prison, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- Atkins, Joseph Ernest, SC, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Bacon, Robert, Jr, NC, Clemency granted, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Baldwin, Brian Keith, AL, 1999 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Bannister, Alan Jeffrey, MO, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Barnabei, Derek Rocco, VA, 2000 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Basile, Daniel, MO, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Bassette, Herbert R, VA, Clemency granted, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Beavers, Thomas H, Jr, VA, Not a Clemency petition, 1997 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Beets, Betty Lou, TX, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Bennett, Ronald B, VA, 1996 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)
- Black, Robert V, Jr, TX, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 13)
- Blackmon, Ricky Don, TX, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 14)
- Boggs, Richard T, VA, 1990 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 15)
- Bolder, Martsay, MO, 1993 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 16)
- Boliek, William T, MO, Execution has been stayed, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 17)
- Breard, Angel Francisco, VA, 1998 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 18)
- Bunch, Timothy Dale, VA, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 19)
- Burket, Russel William, VA, 2000 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 20)
- Byrd, John W, Jr, OH, 2001 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 21)
- Carter, Marcus, NC Clemency granted, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 22)
- Carter, Robert Earl, TX, 1992; 1994; 1998; 2000; Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 23)
- Chambers, James W, MO, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 24)
- Chandler, David R Granted clemency, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 25)
- Chandler, Lance A, Jr, VA, Undated (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 26)
- Chichester, Carl H, VA, 1999 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 27)
- Clark, James Lee, TX, 2006 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 28)
- Coleman, Clydell, TX, 1999 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 39)
- Coleman, Roger Keith, VA Appendices only, 1981-1991 (Box 1 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 30)
- Coleman, Roger Keith, VA Appendices only, 1981-1991 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Coleman, Roger Keith, VA Appendices only, 1981-1991 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- Coleman, Roger Keith, VA Appendices only, 1981-1991 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Coleman, Roger Keith, VA Appendices only, 1981-1991 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Correll, Walter M, Jr, VA, 1996 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Coulson, Robert Otis, TX, 2002 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Davies, Girvies, IL, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)
- Davis, Ralph E, MO, Undated (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 13)
- Dubois, Johnile L, VA, 1998 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 14)
- Eaton, Dennis Wayne, VA, Undated (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 15)
- Edmonds, Dana Ray, VA, 1995 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 16)
- Elliott, Larry Bill, VA, Undated (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 17)
- Evans, Wilbert Lee, VA, 1990 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 18)
- Farriss, Troy Dale, TX, Undated (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 19)
- Faulder, Joseph S, TX, Undated (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 20)
- Fisher, David L, VA, 1999 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 21)
- Fisher, David L, VA, 1999 (Box 2 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 22)
- Fitzgerald, Edward B, VA, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Flowers, Wendell, NC Clemency granted, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- Garza, Juan Raul, US, 2001 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- George, Michael Carl, VA, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Giarratano, Joseph M, VA Clemency granted, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Gosch, Lesley Lee, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Graham, Andre, L, VA, 1999 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Graham, Gary, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Gray, Coleman Wayne, VA, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Green, Harvey Lee, Jr, NC, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Green, Ricky Lee, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Griffin, Larry, MO, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)
- Grubbs, Ricky Lee, MO, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 13)
- Harris, Bobby Lee, NC Death sentence vacated, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 14)
- Harris, George B, MO, 2000 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 15)
- Herrera, Leonel Torres, TX, 1991 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 16)
- Hoke, Ronald Lee, Sr, VA, 1996 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 17)
- Hunter, Bert Leroy, MO, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 18)
- Johns, Stephen, MO, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 19)
- Johnson, Edward Earl, MS, 1987 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 20)
- Johnson, Edward Earl, MS, 1987 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 21)
- Johnson, Richard Charles, SC, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 22)
- Jones, Richard Wayne, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 23)
- Jones, Richard Wayne, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 24)
- Jones, Richard Wayne, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 25)
- Jones, Richard Wayne, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 26)
- Jones, Richard Wayne, TX, Undated (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 27)
- Joseph,Jason Matthew, VA, 1999 (Box 3 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 28)
- Justus, Buddy Earl, VA, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Kilgore, Bruce, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- King, Danny Lee, VA, 1998 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Kruetzer, Paul, MO, 2000 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Lackey, Clarence Allen, TX, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- LaRette, Anthony J, Jr, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Lingar, Stanley, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Mallett, Jerome, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Malone, Kevin, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Mann, Fletcher Thomas, TX, 1995 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Marquez, Mario S, TX, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Mathenia, Chuck, MO Execution has been stayed, 1993 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)
- McGinnis, Glen Charles, TX, 2000 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 13)
- Miller-El, Thomas Joe, TX Death sentence overturned sentenced to life in prison, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 14)
- Mincey, Mitchell Terry, GA, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 15)
- Mitchell, Gerald Lee, TX, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 16)
- Moore, William Neal, GA Clemency granted, 1984 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 17)
- Moore, William Neal, GA Clemency granted, 1984 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 18)
- Moore, William Neal, GA Clemency granted, 1984 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 19)
- Moore, William Neal, GA Clemency granted, 1984 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 20)
- Mueller, Everett Lee, VA, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 21)
- Mueller, Everett Lee, VA, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 22)
- Murphy, Mario Benjamin, VA, 1997 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 23)
- Murray, Robert Anthony, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 24)
- ODell, Joseph Roger, VA, 1994 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 25)
- Owsley, Michael, MO, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 26)
- Paradis, Donald M, ID Clemency granted, 1996 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 27)
- Paradis, Donald M, ID Clemency granted, 1996 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 28)
- Parkus, Steven Wesley, MO Sentence commuted to life in prison, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 29)
- Payne, Joseph P, Sr, VA Clemency granted, 1996 (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 30)
- Peterson, Derick Lynn, VA, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 31)
- Pollard, Roosevelt, Jr, MO Execution has been stayed, Undated (Box 4 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 32)
- Pope, Carlton Jerome, VA, 1997 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Powell, Reginald, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- Poyner, Syvasky L, VA, 1993 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Preston, Elroy, MO Execution has been stayed, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Pyles, Johnny Dean, TX, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Quesinberry, George A, Jr, VA, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Ramdass, Bobby Lee, VA, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Ramsey, Roy, Jr, MO, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Rector, Charles H, TX, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Richardson, Antonio, MO Death sentence overturned, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Roach, Steve Edward, VA, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Roberts, Michael Shane, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)
- Roberts, Roy Michael, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 13)
- Roberts, Roy Michael, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 14)
- Roberts, Roy Michael, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 15)
- Rodden, James E, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 16)
- Roll, Gary Lee, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 17)
- Satcher, Michael C, VA, 1997 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 18)
- Saunders, William, VA Clemency granted, 1997 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 19)
- Savino, Joseph John, VA, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 20)
- Schlup, Lloyd E, Jr, MO New trial no death sentence, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 21)
- Shaw, Bobby Lewis, MO Granted clemency, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 22)
- Sheppard, Mark A, VA, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 23)
- Simmons, Christopher Lee, MO Resentenced to life in prison, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 24)
- Spaziano, Joseph Robert, FL (original housed in the papers of Michael A. Mello), 1985
- Spaziano, Joseph Robert, FL (original housed in the papers of Michael A. Mello), 1985
- Spaziano, Joseph Robert, FL (original housed in the papers of Michael A. Mello), 1985
- Spaziano, Joseph Robert, FL (original housed in the papers of Michael A. Mello), 1985
- Spaziano, Joseph Robert, FL (original housed in the papers of Michael A. Mello), 1985
- Stewart, Kenneth M, Jr, VA, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 25)
- Stockton, Dennis W, VA, 1995 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 26)
- Stoker, David Wayne, TX, 1997 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 27)
- Strickler, Tommy David, VA, 1998 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 28)
- Swann, Calvin Eugene, VA Clemency granted, 1999 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 29)
- Tafero, Jesse Joseph, FL Not a petition, 1984 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 30)
- Thompson, Thomas M, CA, 1997 (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 31)
- Tokar, Jeffrey, MO, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 32)
- Trevino, Joe Mario, TX, Undated (Box 5 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 33)
- Washington, Earl, Jr, VA Clemency granted, 1993 (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- Watkins, Johnny, Jr, VA, Undated (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- Watkins, Ronald L, VA, 1998 (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Weeks, Lonnie, Jr, VA, 2000 (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- West, Robert Wallace, TX, 1997 (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Westley, Anthony Ray, TX, Undated (Box 6 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Westley, Anthony Ray, TX, Undated (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 1)
- White, Billy Dwayne, TX, Undated (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 2)
- White, Clifton Allen, NC, 2001 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 3)
- Williams, Marlon D, VA, 1999 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 4)
- Wilson, Kenneth, VA, 1998 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 5)
- Wise, Joe Louis, Sr, VA, Undated (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 6)
- Workman, Philip, TN, 2000 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 7)
- Wright, Dwayne Allen, VA, 1998 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 8)
- Wright, Freddie Lee, AL, Undated (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 9)
- Yeatts, Ronald Dale, VA, 1999 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 10)
- Young, Mose, Jr, MO, 2000 (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 11)
- Zeitvogel, Richard S, MO, Undated (Box 7 (Capital Punishment Clemency Petitions Collection), Folder 12)